Why do religions fight with each other?
(Questioner) I am a 20 year student
who has been coming here every week ever
since the Kyongju history tour
at the recommendation of a friend.
(Questioner) I have just watched other people
asking questions every week,
but today I have worked up
the courage to ask.
(Questioner) Since childhood, without
being committed to any one religion,
I have been to churches and temples
to hear their teachings.
(Questioner) To me, all religions
seem to be saying the same things.
(Questioner) So, I don't understand
why the religions have conflicts
and seem to oppose each other.
(Questioner) From what I know, the religions
are supposed to provide comfort
and faith to suffering people.
If these are their basic tenets,
I don't understand
why there are such conflicts among them.
First, you asked
why the religions fight with each other?
It's because they all think that only
their doctrines are the right ones.
Second, you said that
it would be better for them
not to have any conflicts
and get along well.
Whose thought is that?
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner) It's my thought.
You are also insisting on
your own thought.
All religions insist
that only their belief systems are right.
So they end up fighting, right?
But to you they are all similar
and they should not fight with each other.
This is whose thought?
Yours.
You, too, are insisting
that they not fight
and there is no need to fight.
It is your insistence
that lead you to join the fight.
"Why are these guys fighting?"
This judgmental thought,
too, is a form of fighting.
Understand?
(Questioner) Yes.
You are in the same boat.
You are thinking in the same way
as those who fight.
"Why are they fighting?
They're crazy to fight like that
when all the religions are the same."
These are the thinking processes
that lead to fighting.
(Questioner) I understand.
Wait! If you're certain you got it,
then turn the mic over.
If not, ask again.
That what we're here for: Q and A
(Questioner) Well, then..
Don't let go of the mic squeamishly,
if you're not completely clear.
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner) Then,
isn't there a way not to fight?
(Audience Laughter)
Yes, there is.
(Questioner) What is that?
Huh?
(Questioner) How to..?
How?
Just observe them.
(Questioner) I see.
(Audience Laughter)
To find a way not to fight?
Want to find a way not to fight?
"Isn't there a way for Buddhists
and Christians not to fight?"
If this is your question,
you are on the wrong track.
If you don't quarrel with the world,
there is no fight.
Do you understand what I am saying?
(Questioner) Yes.
You are actually arguing with the world.
"Why are you guys fighting?" you argue.
So, the way not to fight
is to leave them alone.
Just observe, "Oh, they are fighting."
Without judging whether it is good or bad,
just witness them as they are.
Thinking that "all religions are the same,
so why are they fighting?"
is having an argument with those people.
They are fighting in the same way
you are arguing with them.
One side argues,
"They should believe in God;
why don't they believe in God?"
The other side argues,
"How do you believe in God
who doesn't even exist?"
And what about you?
You quarrel with them about fighting:
"Why are you fighting?"
(Audience Laughter)
This is how it continues.
When you are obsessed with being right,
a fight ensues.
So, as I said before, don't argue with
others about what they ought to do.
Drop your own thought,
then there is one less person fighting.
When you join two people fighting,
there will be three people fighting.
But if you join without arguing,
you could help end the fight.
Fighting happen this way.
The way not to fight starts with me
when I do not engage in the fight.
Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes, thank you.
Young people don't hold grudges.
(Audience Laughter)